{'title': '1. Percy Shelley û Ozymandias', 'words': 171, 'data': 'I met a traveller from an antique landWho said: æTwo vast and trunkless legs of stoneStand in the desert. Near them, on the sand,Half sunk, a shattered visage lies, whose frown,And wrinkled lip, and sneer of cold command,Tell that its sculptor well those passions readWhich yet survive, stamped on these lifeless things,The hand that mocked them and the heart that fed.And on the pedestal these words appear ùôMy name is Ozymandias, king of kings:Look on my works, ye Mighty, and despair!öNothing beside remains. Round the decayOf that colossal wreck, boundless and bareThe lone and level sands stretch far away.ÆKicking off the list is\xa0Ozymandias, a bleak sonnet written in 1818. It describes a statue isolated in a desert which used to mark a great civilisation. A popular interpretation is that Shelley is pointing out the uselessness of human accomplishments: nothing lasts. Ozymandias\xa0is also the title for an episode Breaking Bad,\xa0in which protagonist Walter White is abandoned in the desert, left with only a minuscule percentage of his accumulated wealth. How very fitting.'}
{'title': '2. Robert Frost û Fire & Ice\xa0', 'words': 99, 'data': 'Some say the world will end in fire,Some say in ice.From what IÆve tasted of desireI hold with those who favour fire.But if it had to perish twice,I think I know enough of hateTo say that for destruction iceIs also greatAnd would suffice.Of course poetic mastermind Robert Frost was going to make his way onto this list. Interestingly, this 1920 poem was penned just two years after WWI. In the space of nine lines, and with the aid of some vivid juxtaposition, Frost perfectly captures that post-war uncertainty and existential aches that many would have felt during this time.'}
{'title': '3. Emily Dickinson û I heard a fly buzz û when I died\xa0', 'words': 155, 'data': 'I heard a Fly buzz û when I died ûThe Stillness in the RoomWas like the Stillness in the Air ûBetween the Heaves of Storm ûThe Eyes around û had wrung them dry ûAnd Breaths were gathering firmFor that last Onset û when the KingBe witnessed û in the Room ûI willed my Keepsakes û Signed awayWhat portion of me beAssignable û and then it wasThere interposed a Fly ûWith Blue û uncertain û stumbling Buzz ûBetween the light û and me ûAnd then the Windows failed û and thenI could not see to see ûWhen it comes to Dickinson, the topic of death is commonly explored. However, her approaches are so unique that you have to admire the creativity. This poem explores death from the past tense, recalling the moment it happened to great effect. With some signature Dickinson dashes for rhythm and puzzlement, this is one to read again û again û again.'}
{'title': '4. William Shakespeare û Shall I Compare Thee To A SummerÆs Day?', 'words': 196, 'data': 'Shall I compare thee to a summerÆs day?Thou art more lovely and more temperate.Rough winds do shake the darling buds of May,And summerÆs lease hath all too short a date.Sometime too hot the eye of heaven shines,And often is his gold complexion dimmed;And every fair from fair sometime declines,By chance, or natureÆs changing course, untrimmed;But thy eternal summer shall not fade,Nor lose possession of that fair thou owÆst,Nor shall death brag thou wandÆrest in his shade,When in eternal lines to Time thou growÆst.So long as men can breathe, or eyes can see,So long lives this, and this gives life to thee.If youÆre not familiar with any of the names on the list so far, do not fear, Shakespeare is here! Also dubbed Sonnet 18, this short poem is more than just about love, itÆs about the memory of it, and a very real, human fear that we, in time, will be forgotten. One of the most meaningful short poems written, throw in some hyperbole, repetition, and a couple of striking similes, and you have a sonnet for the ages. On another note, did you know that Shakespeare had an affinity for weed? More on that here.'}
{'title': '5. Langston Hughes û So Tired Blues\xa0', 'words': 73, 'data': 'With the sun in my handGonna throw the sunWay across the land-Cause IÆm tired,Tired as I can beHughes was one of the earliest pioneers of jazz poetry. For that alone, he could have made this list, but this poem is a personal favourite. The desire to speed up time to get to bed earlier is such a universal feeling, and Langston describes it with such gleeful imagery. ItÆs a challenge not to grin.'}
{'title': '6. Edgar Allan Poe û A Dream Within A Dream\xa0', 'words': 164, 'data': 'Take this kiss upon the brow!And, in parting from you now,Thus much let me avow-You are not wrong, who deemThat my days have been a dream;Yet if hope has flown awayIn a night, or in a day,In a vision, or in none,Is it therefore the less gone?All that we see or seemIs but a dream within a dream.I stand amid the roarOf a surf-tormented shore,And I hold within my handGrains of the golden sand-How few! yet how they creepThrough my fingers to the deep,While I weep- while I weep!O God! can I not graspThem with a tighter clasp?O God! can I not saveOne from the pitiless wave?Is all that we see or seemBut a dream within a dream?Move over Inception, Edgar Allen Poe did it first. This poem of uncertainty is a riddle and a half, with the protagonist grappling with the strings of reality. ItÆs essentially the literary text of The Matrix, and, like many of Edgar Allen PoeÆs literary efforts, itÆs ingenious.'}
{'title': '7. John Donne û\xa0 No Man Is an Island', 'words': 120, 'data': 'No man is an island,Entire of itself,Every man is a piece of the continent,A part of the main.If a clod be washed away by the sea,Europe is the less.As well as if a promontory were.As well as if a manor of thy friendÆsOr of thine own were:Any manÆs death diminishes me,Because I am involved in mankind,And therefore never send to know for whom the bell tolls;It tolls for thee.Finally, we reach DonneÆs 400-year-old masterpiece. Calling for unity, DonneÆs comparison of people to countries is the sort of anti-isolation remark that still resonates strongly today. The opening line from this memorable excerpt was even used as a hashtag during the Brexit debate. Who said poetry is a dead art? Not I.'}
{'title': '8. Ogden Nash û A Word To Husbands\xa0', 'words': 75, 'data': 'To keep your marriage brimmingWith love in the loving cup,Whenever youÆre wrong, admit it;Whenever youÆre right, shut up.Nash always claimed to think in rhyme, but itÆs his truthful tongue-in-cheek execution that gets A Word To Husbands on the list. The nagging temptation to say ôI told you soö is ever-present in relationships, most likely since the dawn of time. However, the one thing you should never ever, ever, do, is speak it. Wise words, Nash.'}
{'title': '9. Natasha Tretheway û Housekeeping', 'words': 144, 'data': 'We mourn the broken things, chair legswrenched from their seats, chipped plates,the threadbare clothes. We work the magicof glue, drive the nails, mend the holes.We save what we can, melt small piecesof soap, gather fallen pecans, keep neck bonesfor soup. Beating rugs against the house,we watch dust, lit like stars, spreadingacross the yard. Late afternoon, we drawthe blinds to cool the rooms, drive the bugsout. My mother irons, singing, lost in reverie.I mark the pages of a mail-order catalog,listen for passing cars. All-day we watchfor the mail, some news from a distant place.From the poet laureate, Natasha Tretheway, comes Housekeeping: a striking painting of visceral imagery and pulse. An author of five poetry collections, Tretheway finds inspiration in her upbringing and personal hardships. The result of her inward reflection and memory often evokes feelings of raw honesty and newfound clarity, particularly with this piece.'}
{'title': '10. Strickland Gillilan û Lines on the Antiquity of Microbes (also known as Fleas)', 'words': 68, 'data': 'Adam.Had ÆemNo list of the greatest short poems ever would be complete withoutà the shortest poem ever. While itÆs not quite a one line poem, there are some other contenders, such as Aram SaroyanÆs four-legged m, but the spot had to go to Gillilan. Using just three words, and a ridiculously scientific title, he scores a quick laugh. Plus, his brief and uselessly profound revelation was probably true.'}
{'title': '11. William Carlos Williams û This Is Just To Say', 'words': 88, 'data': 'I have eatenthe plumsthat were inthe iceboxand whichyou were probablysavingfor breakfastForgive methey were deliciousso sweetand so coldA simple and peculiar poem, This Is Just To Say also has multiple interpretations. Some see it as a casual apology to his wife, others compare it to the story of Eve and the tree of the knowledge of good and evil in the Bible, and some see it as simply a celebration of finding delight in the small things. ThereÆs no right answer, but its evocative nature makes for excellent penmanship.'}
{'title': '12. Dr. Seuss û Green Eggs & Ham\xa0', 'words': 133, 'data': 'I do not like them in a boxI do not like them with a foxI do not like them in a houseI do not like them with a mouseI do not like them here or thereI do not like them anywhereI do not like green eggs and hamI do not like them Sam I amDr. Seuss: the writer who served as the introduction to exceptional illustration and poetry for countless children. For that, he needed to be on this list, even if meant just quoting a page from one of his best. SeussÆs method of injecting whimsy and absurdity into rhyme and meter made for some memorable childrenÆs books, distinct enough to earn impressive sales and staying power. Warning: you should definitely not watch Henry Rollins tear this Dr. Seuss classic to shreds.'}
{'title': '13. Pablo Neruda û\xa0If You Forget Me', 'words': 250, 'data': 'I want you to knowone thing.You know how this is:if I lookat the crystal moon, at the red branchof the slow autumn at my window,if I touchnear the firethe impalpable ashor the wrinkled body of the log,everything carries me to you,as if everything that exists,aromas, light, metals,were little boatsthat sailtoward those isles of yours that wait for me.Well, now,if little by little you stop loving meI shall stop loving you little by little.If suddenlyyou forget medo not look for me,for I shall already have forgotten you.If you think it long and mad,the wind of bannersthat passes through my life,and you decideto leave me at the shoreof the heart where I have roots,rememberthat on that day,at that hour,I shall lift my armsand my roots will set offto seek another land.Butif each day,each hour,you feel that you are destined for mewith implacable sweetness,if each day a flowerclimbs up to your lips to seek me,ah my love, ah my own,in me all that fire is repeated,in me nothing is extinguished or forgotten,my love feeds on your love, beloved,and as long as you live it will be in your armswithout leaving mine.If you happen to forget this poem, remember one thing û love is as fickle as it is passionate. Chilean Nobel Prize Winner Neruda switches the tone of If You Forget Me from romantic, to darkly honest, back to romantic. The result is an incredibly realistic passage on love and how even in its beauty, it can waver, or even completely disintegrate. *Shudders*.'}
{'title': '14. Joyce Kilmer û Trees', 'words': 149, 'data': 'I think that I shall never seeA poem lovely as a tree.A tree whose hungry mouth is prestAgainst the earthÆs sweet flowing breast;A tree that looks at God all day,And lifts her leafy arms to pray;A tree that may in summer wearA nest of robins in her hair;Upon whose bosom snow has lain;Who intimately lives with rain.Poems are made by fools like me,But only God can make a tree.WeÆve received some memorable artistic portrayals of trees over the years. The Ents in Lord Of The Rings are ancient and wise and Shel SilversteinÆs The Giving Tree is utterly heartbreaking (if you know, you know). However, KilmerÆs portrayal positions trees in the highest regard. The human-like qualities he gives trees are metaphorically faultless, and the final couplet drives home his argumentsÆ significance even further, by claiming the medium heÆs utilising isnÆt even worthy for such a beautiful feature of nature.'}
{'title': '15. Derek Walcott û Love After Love\xa0', 'words': 147, 'data': 'The time comewhen, with elationyou will greet yourself arrivingat your own door, in your own mirrorand each will smile at the otherÆs welcome,and say, sit here. Eat.You will love again the stranger who was your self.Give wine. Give bread. Give back your heartto itself, to the stranger who has loved youall your life, whom you ignoredfor another, who knows you by heart.Take down the love letters from the bookshelf,the photographs, the desperate notes,peel your own image from the mirror.Sit. Feast on your life.There have been several love poems on this list, but\xa0Love After Love is the first to explicitly explore the underrated importance of loving oneÆs self. As Cher once said, it appears there is life after love. The hopeful sentiment from poet and playwright Walcott is so compelling, that the piecesÆ outro line has likely fallen victim to the fancy font, inspirational quote portion of Tumblr.'}
{'title': '16. Robert Burn û A Red, Red, Rose', 'words': 157, 'data': 'O my Luve is like a red, red roseThatÆs newly sprung in June;O my Luve is like the melodyThatÆs sweetly played in tune.So fair art thou, my bonnie lass,So deep in luve am I;And I will luve thee still, my dear,Till aÆ the seas gang dry.Till aÆ the seas gang dry, my dear,And the rocks melt wiÆ the sun;I will love thee still, my dear,While the sands oÆ life shall run.And fare thee weel, my only luve!And fare thee weel awhile!And I will come again, my luve,Though it were ten thousand mile.The highly famed romantic expression of comparing a womenÆs cheeks to a rose is believed by most to have begun here. At least, in written form. This iconic poem from the 18th-century bard reads much like the lyrics to a love song, so itÆs unsurprising to hear that the last remaining troubadour Bob Dylan called this poem his single biggest inspiration. Now, thatÆs some high-calibre praise.'}
{'title': '17. Margaret Atwood û You Fit Into Me', 'words': 87, 'data': 'you fit into melike a hook into an eyea fish hookan open eye\xa0So few words. So much evocation. Atwood positions a tightly knit couple as hooked together, but while a hook is strong, it isnÆt comfortable. I believe Atwood is exploring the idea of imbalanced relationships here. Pain and pleasure are often juxtaposed, but Atwood recognises that these feelings are blurred. A relationship may feel snug and tight, but what if youÆve merely been hooked like a fish, just waiting to be killed at the opportune moment.'}
{'title': '18. Leunig û How To Get There', 'words': 127, 'data': 'Go to the end of the path until you get to the gate.Go through the gate and head straight out towards the horizon.Keep going towards the horizon.Sit down and have a rest every now and again,But keep on going, just keep on with it.Keep on going as far as you can.ThatÆs how you get there.\xa0The rat race of modern life is exhausting. Every success brings new problems, and every problem leads to new successes. Like the horizon itself, our final destination often feels out of reach û and thatÆs because it is. There is no grand finale. No encore. ItÆs the choices we make along the way that embed meaning into our existential crisis. Who better than to expose our fragilities than a self-described vaudevillian like Leunig.'}
{'title': '19. Sylvia Plath û\xa0Metaphors', 'words': 137, 'data': 'IÆm a riddle in nine syllables,An elephant, a ponderous house,A melon strolling on two tendrils.O red fruit, ivory, fine timbers!This loafÆs big with its yeasty rising.MoneyÆs new-minted in this fat purse.IÆm a means, a stage, a cow in calf.IÆve eaten a bag of green apples,Boarded the train thereÆs no getting off.Nine lines with nine syllables each. The structure itself is perhaps the biggest clue of all regarding the subject of PlathÆs unsettling playfulness. Ask yourself, what takes nine months to arrive? An elephant, rising yeast, a ponderous houseà what could these possibly have in common? The posthumous Pulitzer Prize winner is addressing pregnancy; an ongoing point of interest for the tragic poet. Suddenly, the comparisons turn from humorous to sobering, as Plath positions herself as a carrier with only one sole purpose, and ôthereÆs no getting offö.'}
{'title': '20. Anais Nin û Risk', 'words': 95, 'data': 'And then the day came,when the riskto remain tightin a budwas more painfulthan the riskit tookto blossom.When was the day you stopped conforming and started leading your own life? For me, it came right after high school. Seeking the approval of others whilst sacrificing my own identity? Yeah, that wasnÆt going to cut it anymore. It was time to take the plunge, aka, ôblossomö, and discard any remnants of external expectations. As clichÚ as it sounds, itÆs a vital life lesson that comes with time, and few have described this realisation as powerfully as Nin.'}
{'title': '21. Maya Angelou û Awaking in New York', 'words': 97, 'data': 'Curtains forcing their will against the wind,children sleep,exchanging dreams with seraphim. The citydrags itself awake on subway straps; andI, an alarm, awake as a rumor of war,lie stretching into dawn, unasked and unheeded.In less than fifteen lines, Maya AngelouÆs masterful words paint a portrait of the dizzying breadth of New York City, exuding a sense of both wistfulness and melancholia at the site of an awakening metropolis. She lays bare the adrenaline of being wrapped into the tapestry of a bustling city, whilst simultaneously exposing the overwhelming sense of loneliness found in these most dazzling of places.'}
{'title': '22. William Butler Yeats û Death', 'words': 109, 'data': 'Nor dread nor hope attendA dying animal;A man awaits his endDreading and hoping all;Many times he died,Many times rose again.A great man in his prideConfronting murderous menCasts derision uponSupersession of breath;He knows death to the bone ûMan has created death.In the shortest of YeatsÆs many poems, in just a dozen lines, he examines death and our attitude towards it. In contrasting an animalÆs ignorance of its own mortality, to our propensity to fill the mind with man-made ideas, whether it is pride, or thoughts of death. Yeates makes fine use of depicting presence, or rather the lack of, when he poetically poses that thoughts can create an unhappy reality.'}
{'title': '23. Thomas Hardy û How Great My Grief', 'words': 150, 'data': 'How great my grief, my joys how few,Since first it was my fate to know thee!Have the slow years not brought to viewHow great my grief, my joys how few,Nor memory shaped old times anew,Nor loving-kindness helped to show theeHow great my grief, my joys how few,Since first it was my fate to know thee?One of the most famous eight-line poems, also known as triolet, by one of the most famous authors of the late 19th century. HardyÆs How Great My Grief encapsulates what it means to feel the impact of what it means to love and lose someone, and that not even time, nor the kindness of friends or family can help to alleviate the pain and suffering. Hardys use the word fate to share his idea, that there must be a reason or a purpose in his pain, even if he canÆt at first know what that is.'}
